<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> J. P. HARLEY,<note>John Pritt Harley (1786-1858; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), actor and singer. Stage-manager and leading comedian at the St James’s Theatre from Sep 36. CD added the non-singing part of Martin Stokes to <hi rend="italic">The Village Coquettes</hi> for him and dedicated the play to him (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1, pp. 151n, 167n).</note> [?8 NOVEMBER 1837]</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-13</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Charles Dickens Museum. Date: CD moved to Doughty St in Apr 37; he returned from Brighton (his only visit in the Doughty Street period) on 7 Nov 37 and presumably answered Harley the next day; handwriting and form of address support.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id=" friends|social engagements"> friends|social engagements</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Doughty St.</placeName>
               <date when="1837-11-08">Wednesday Evening</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Harley.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am more sorry than I can tell you, that I did not receive your invitation within a more convenient distance than Brighton<note>CD had been in Brighton, 31 Oct-7 Nov, after finishing <hi rend="italic">Pickwick.</hi></note> – especially as I am truly anxious to see more of you, and not to perpetuate our present angel interviews.<note>CD plays on “angel visits”, which are “few and far between”; proverbial at least by the eighteenth century: <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi> cites Robert Blair, The Grave (1743), and Thomas Campbell, <hi rend="italic">The Pleasures of Hope</hi> (1797).</note> Can you take a family dinner with me, next Sunday at four? Forster dines with us, and a man named Thackeray<note>William Makepeace Thackeray (1811-63; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>). First met CD in Apr 36, when he hoped to succeed Seymour as illustrator of Pickwick: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1, p. 305n. Rejected, but contributed to <hi rend="italic">Bentley’s Miscellany</hi> (see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1, pp. 293n, 305 &amp; n).</note> whom perhaps you know; no one else. It will afford me very great pleasure to hear from you that we may hope to see you.</p>
<p>J. P. Harley Esqre</p>
	<closer>
            <salute>In haste Believe me | Ever Faithfully Yours 
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>