<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> LADY HOLLAND,<note>Elizabeth Vassall Fox (1770-1845; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), wife of the 3rd Baron Holland; the famous and autocratic hostess of Holland House: see Pilgrim Letters 1, p. 412n and Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 2, p. 63n. Holland House, on Kensington High Street, its grounds now Holland Park, was extensively damaged in the Second World War: see Lord Ilchester, <hi rend="italic">Chronicles of Holland House</hi>, 1937, Chs. 16 &amp; 17.</note> [?12 AUGUST 1838-11 DECEMBER 1839]</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p> Text from facsimile in Sotheby’s on-line catalogue, 2002; MS (fragment) 1 p.; address and date given at foot of page. Date: after CD’s first visit to Holland House, 12 Aug 38 (a Sunday); before 12 Dec 39, when he moved to Devonshire Terrace.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id=""></interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>48 Doughty Street</placeName>
               <date when="1838-08-12">Wednesday Morning</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>As I am (fortunately for myself) both in town and disengaged next Friday, I shall be most happy to avail myself of your and Lord Holland’s kind invitation.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Very Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS<note>The top of the MS has been torn off, leaving traces of descenders.</note></persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>