<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> John Forster<note>John Forster (1812-76; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), CD’s closest friend, literary and legal advisor, and co-executor of his will; author of the authorised biography <hi rend="italic">The Life of Charles Dickens</hi> (1872-4). See Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1 p. 239n.</note>, 6 April 1838</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-02-18</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Sotheby’s New York on-line catalogue, December 2001. Date: after CD’s first meeting with TalfourdRachel, eldest daughter of John Towill Rutt, married (1822) Thomas Noon Talfourd. in Spring 1837, but not on mourning paper which CD used for nearly a year after Mary Hogarth’s death (April 1837); handwriting points to Spring 1838; “always” in subscription and “Esquire” in full, support 1838.          </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="friends|social engagements|Bentley's Miscellany|Oliver Twist|Nicholas Nickleby">friends|social engagements|Bentley's Miscellany|Oliver Twist|Nicholas Nickleby</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>48 Doughty Street</placeName>
               <date when="1838-04-06">Wednesday Morning<note>Short double strokes under “Morning”.</note></date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Forster</salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I have not sent your note to Mrs. Talfourd,<note><note>(1795-1854; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), barrister and writer: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1, pp. 290n, 315<hi rend="italic">n</hi>. CD had first met Talfourd in Spring 1837; the arrangements proposed support a date when CD knew the Talfourds well</note></note> for I found on reflection that I could not possibly dine out on Monday – or indeed sooner than Saturday,<note>Throughout Spring 1838 CD was editing <hi rend="italic">Bentley’s Miscellany</hi>, writing <hi rend="italic">Oliver Twist</hi>, and planning and writing <hi rend="italic">Nicholas Nickleby</hi>: he clearly needed ten days to complete his stint before a deadline of the 19th of the month.</note> having in mind my work. Will you say how much pleasure it will afford me to dine in Russell Square on that day, if convenient?</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Always Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS | John Forster Esquire</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>