<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MISS CAMILLA TOULMIN,<note>Camilla Dufour Toulmin (1812-95; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), later Mrs Newton Crosland. Prolific novelist and contributor to periodicals from 1838.</note> [LATE JANUARY 1839]</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-22</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Phillip Pirages. Address (envelope): Miss Toulmin, 5 New Ormond Street. Date: news of the death of Mrs Maclean (“L.E.L.”; see below) was published in the London Courier, 1 Jan 39; Camilla Toulmin’s lines appeared in Bentley’s Miscellany, Feb 39.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="Bentley's Miscellany|publishing">Bentley's Miscellany|publishing</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
	<address>
		<addrLine>5 New Ormond Street
		</addrLine>
	</address>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Doughty Street </placeName>
               <date when="">Friday afternoon<note>Address and date at foot of letter.</note></date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Mr. Dickens presents his compliments to Miss Toulmin and begs to assure her that she shall see his proof of the lines on Mrs. Maclean’s death,<note>Letitia Elizabeth Landon (1802-38; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>); poetess as “L.E.L.” Briefly engaged to John Forster, 1835. Married George Maclean, Governor of Cape Coast Colony, 1838; went with him to the Cape Coast, where she died mysteriously, Oct 38. <hi rend="italic">Her Life and Literary Remains</hi>, 2 vols, 1841, by Laman Blanchard.</note> directly it reaches his hands. Mr. Dickens may take this opportunity of saying that its return at Miss Toulmin’s earliest convenience will greatly oblige him.<note>Toulmin’s poem, “On the Death of Mrs. Maclean, (L.E.L.)”, was published in the Miscellany, Feb 39, V, 144.
</note></p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>