<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> M. LOUIS PRÉVOST,<note>Louis Augustin Prévost (1790-1858; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), linguist, of 25 New Street, Dorset Square.  linguist. Born at Troyes; settled in England 1823; taught languages 1823-43; and served on the British Museum staff 1843-55, where he catalogued the collection of Chinese books. He mastered over 40 languages. He is referred to in the <hi rend="italic">Critic, XVII</hi> (1858), 220, and in Robert Cowtan, <hi rend="italic">Memories of the British Museum</hi>, 1872, p. 360, as CD's French tutor; and this is supported by payments to him of £2.7.6 on 8 Dec 37, £3.3 on 1 Feb and £2.16 on 28 Feb 40, recorded in CD's account-book (MS Messrs Coutts). W. J. Carlton suggests that he may have been the French master at Wellington House, described in "Our School" (Household Words, 11 Oct 51, IV, 51): see "Dickens Studies French", <hi rend="italic">Dickensian</hi>, LIX, (1963), 21-7. See also Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 2, p. 461n.</note> [?EARLY DECEMBER 1839]</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-07</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in unidentified on line catalogue. Address: M. Prevost. Date: just before the move to Devonshire Terrace; CD’s first letter from there is dated 12 Dec (a Thursday), so possibly the Friday before (6 Dec).</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="">education|family|France</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Doughty Street|Friday – late at night.</placeName>
               <date when=""></date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I regret that I did not know in sufficient time to-day to write to you, that I could not have my usual pleasant hour with you in the morning. I find, however, that some matters of business connected with our removal from hence, call me from home so early, and will occupy me so long, that I have no alternative but to postpone our reading.<note>i.e. class or study session (as in “reading” a subject at University).</note> We have now two or three readings to make up, and I hope we shall soon be able to redeem them. My brother<note>Frederic Dickens (1820-68): see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1, p. 47n.</note> shall call on you before Wednesday with our new address. Meantime believe me </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS|M. Prevost<note>i.e. Monsieur Prévost.</note></persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>