<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> HENRY COLBURN,<note>Henry Colburn (d.1855), publisher and magazine proprietor. Founded the <hi rend="italic">New Monthly Magazine</hi> (1814), <hi 		rend="italic">Literary Gazette</hi> (1817), <hi rend="italic">Court Journal</hi> (1829), and held interests in the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum and Sunday Times</hi>.
 	Brought out the first editions of Evelyn's Diary 1819 and Pepys's <hi rend="italic"> Diary</hi> 1825. Disraeli, Bulwer, Hook, Marrya Ainsworth and Lady Morgan were among the authors he published. 	Had a highly unsatisfactory partnership with Richard Bentley 1829-32. His opportunism earned him many enemies, <hi rend="italic">Fraser's Magazine</hi> describing him as the 'Prince Paramount of 	Puffers and Quacks' (I [1830], 320). Published The <hi rend="italic">Pic Nic Papers</hi>, edited by CD, 1841. His widow, Eliza Ann, married John Forster in 1856.</note> 30 MAY 1840</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">Pic Nic Papers,editing,travel
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-01-30</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="">Pic Nic Papers,editing,travel</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
		<address>
		
		</address>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Elm Cottage, Petersham, Surrey<note>D had rented Elm Cottage from 30 Apr to 31 Aug 1839.</note></placeName>
               <date when="">May 30th 1840</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>
What do you wish me to do with the tale<note>Unidentified; possibly a contribution for CD to consider for inclusion in <hi rend="italic">The Pic Nic Papers</hi>, contracted for publication by Colburn in 1838 but not published until 1841.</note> which you left here t'other day? As it was left without any note or explanation, I am quite at sea about it.
	</p>
	 <p>
	I am going to Broadstairs for a month, early on Monday Morning. If you wish to communicate with me on the subject, a letter addressed to me there, will find me readily.
	</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
			Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>