<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> SIR MARTIN SHEE,<note>Sir Martin Archer Shee (1769-1850; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), portrait painter; RA 1800, President RA 1830-50. He and CD had met at the Artists’ Benevolent Fund dinner, 12 May 38 (Speeches, ed. K. J. Fielding, p. 2). See further Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 2, p. 262n</note> 9 JUNE 1841</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-11</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Swann Auction Galleries on-line catalogue, 2009.
</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="social issues">social issues</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Devonshire Terrace.</placeName>
               <date when="1841-06-09"> June The Ninth 1841.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sir Martin.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I thank you very much, for your kind and ready acquiescence in the matter of the Sanatorium.<note>A sanatorium, promoted by Dr Southwood Smith (below), for “the Lodging, Nursing and Care of Sick Persons of the Middle Classes” (1842 Prospectus); opened at Devonshire House, York Gate (close to CD’s house at Devonshire Terrace), Apr 42. See further Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 2, p. 165n.</note> I should have mentioned when I sent you Doctor Smith’s<note>Thomas Southwood Smith, MD (1788-1861; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), sanitary reformer. From 1820 practised medicine in London; the main founder of the Health of Towns Association, 1839. See further Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 2, p. 164n.</note> pamphlet<note><hi rend="italic">The Sanatorium; A Self-Supporting Establishment for the Lodging, Nursing, and Cure of Sick Persons of Both Sexes</hi>, 1840.</note> and conveyed to you the committees<note>Apostrophe omitted by CD. CD was on the Committee of the Sanatorium and was concerned to recruit additional “names” (see To Shee, 3 June 41, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 2, p. 293).</note> request, that the design—honestly—was not upon your pocket, but upon the sanction of your name and station. Let me thank you again with great cordiality, and beg you to believe me</p><p>“ “ “<note>The MS apparently shows ditto marks below Shee’s name; if so, indicating his address as it would appear on the envelope (32 Cavendish Square).
</note></p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Sir Martin Archer Shee
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>