<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MARION ELY,<note>Marion Elizabeth Ely (1820-1913), daughter of Charles Ely and Sara, née Rutt; niece of Rachel Talfourd (1792-1875), wife of CD's friend Thomas Noon Talfourd (1795-1854).</note> 2 DECEMBER 1844</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile on the website of John Wilson Manuscripts Ltd. Address: Miss Ely | 56 Russell Square.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="The Chimes|travel|friends|social engagements">The Chimes|travel|friends|social engagements</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName> Piazza Coffee House<note>George Cuttriss’s Piazza Coffee House and Hotel, Covent Garden (North Side). CD was in London, 30 Nov-8 Dec, having travelled from Genoa where he was living with his family, to oversee the printing of The Chimes; he also gave two readings of the Christmas Book, 3 and 5 December: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 234 n6. Richard Barham noted on 5 Dec that CD read <hi rend="italic">The Chimes</hi> “with remarkable effect...from the proofs” (Life and Letters of <hi rend="italic">the Rev. Richard Harris Barham</hi>by his Son, 1870, II, 191).</note></placeName>
               <date when="1844-12-02">Monday December Second 1844

</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Miss Ely.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>The sight of your familiar and graceful hand did me scarcely less good last night, than the sight of your something more than graceful face had done me in the morning. I shall be delighted to dine in Russell Square on Saturday; and beg my sincerest regards to all belonging there.<note>The Talfourd family.</note>  </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Believe me Ever / Faithfully Yours 
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS|Miss Ely.  </persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>