<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MARION ELY,<note>Marion Elizabeth Ely (1820-1913), daughter of Charles Ely and Sara, née Rutt; niece of Rachel Talfourd (1792-1875), wife of CD's friend Thomas Noon Talfourd (1795-1854).</note> 22 JANUARY 1844</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-02-24</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Extract and facsimile(aa) in Bonham’s catalogue, 23 March 2004: MS 2 pp; envelope; addressed Miss Ely; dated Devonshire Terrace, 22 January 1844.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="publishing|health|family|magic|social engagements|Bentley's">publishing|health|family|magic|social engagements|Bentley's Miscellany</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName></placeName>
               <date when=""></date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Always Faithfully Yours</salute>
         </opener>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Regretting that his sister-in-law’s recovered health<note>Georgina Hogarth’s recovery means that her birthday (22 January) will be celebrated; if she had been still ill, CD might reasonably have gone out.</note> means that he cannot go to Barham’s</hi><note>“Barnham’s” in the source: the Rev. Richard Harris Barham (1788-1845; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), author of <hi rend="italic">The Ingoldsby Legends</hi> (1840; 2nd and 3rd series, 1847); contributor to <hi rend="italic">Bentley’s Miscellany</hi>. Friend and advisor to Richard Bentley and at Bentley’s request mediated in the publisher’s quarrel with CD, in Jan 39: see further Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1, p. 279n. Barham had dined at CD’s on 2 Dec 43, when Marion and the Talfourds were among those present: Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 3, p. 602 and <hi rend="italic">n</hi>.</note>…with an ill grace and a strong grudge, I must resign that blessed corner whereof you give me a glimpse. ...I must get over leaf to give due effect to an Announcement... The Guinea Pig Is Dead He left it in his Will, that he thought Conjuring had been the Death of him.<note>3CD began conjuring in Dec 42 (see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 3, p. 416 and n). This guinea pig is presumably the one featured at Nina Macready’s birthday party, 26 Dec 43, where among other tricks described by Jane Welsh Carlyle, CD changed “a box full of bran into a box full of – a live-guinea-pig!” (<hi rend="italic">The Collected Letters of Thomas and Jane Welsh Carlyle</hi>, ed Clyde de L. Ryals, Kenneth J. Fielding <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1990, vol. 17, p. 220).</note>  </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Miss Ely. 
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>