<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> DR GEORGE SHRENBURGH,<note>Unidentified.</note> 9 JANUARY 1844</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Replaces extract in Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 17. Text from facsimile in Christie’s, New York catalogue, April 2003.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="Germany|publishing">Germany|publishing</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Devonshire Terrace</placeName>
               <date when="1844-01-09">Ninth January 1844</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am exceedingly sorry to say, in reply to your note, that it is quite out of my power to give you the employment you seek. I believe my publishers facilitate the German translations<note>For translations up to 1841, see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 2, p. 43<hi rend="italic">n</hi>.</note> of my writings, by sending early sheets to certain German Booksellers.<note>Publishers of translations included Weber and Wigand of Leipzig, Franckh and Krabbe of Stuttgart, and Vieweg of Brunswick: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4 p. 17n.</note> But this is matter of arrangement between them. The books are translated in Germany; and the enterprise is not mine, or my publishers, but originated with German houses of business.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Your obedient Servant
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS| Dr. George Shrenburgh.</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>