<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> JAMES HEYWOOD,<note>James Heywood (1810-97; see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 404n), one of the founders of the Manchester Athenaeum and its first President.</note> 17 OCTOBER 1845</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-02-17</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Private.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="health,public recognition,celebrity,social engagements,trave">health,public recognition,celebrity,social engagements,travel</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>London, 1 Devonshire Terrace| York Gate Regent’s Park</placeName>
               <date when="1845-10-17">Seventeenth October 1845</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am exceedingly obliged to you for your kind invitation. It would be a great pleasure to me to accept it; but my movements are so exceedingly uncertain, my arrival in Manchester<note>CD had agreed to attend the Manchester Athenaeum’s soirée on 23 Oct, to support Talfourd, the evening’s President. Heywood evidently asked CD to do something else than just attend: see also <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Leech, 17 Oct, and, for the soirée, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 413<hi rend="italic">nn</hi>.</note> so dependant on circumstances, and the period of my stay so very short, that I deem it best to hold myself aloof from all engagements there. I have many occupations at this moment of a very pressing nature; and Mrs Dickens being unwell besides, and very near her confinement,<note>Catherine gave birth to Alfred D’Orsay Tennyson Dickens on 28 Oct. CD had already made clear her pregnancy meant his visit to Manchester must be brief: five days later, he withdrew altogether (<hi rend="italic">To</hi> Berlyn, 22 Oct).</note> I am really afraid to make engagements.</p>

         <closer>
            <salute>I am always, My Dear Sir,Very Faithfully yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS,James Heywood Esquire</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>