<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> ANGUS FLETCHER,<note>Angus Fletcher of Dunans (1805-75), advocate; a cousin of the sculptor and friend of CD of the same name. In writing to Macready, enclosing this letter, CD called him “a capital fellow to know”; Macready called on Fletcher, 3 Mar (To Macready, 27 Feb 46; Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 509 &amp; <hi rend="italic">n</hi>.).</note> 27 FEBRUARY 1846 </title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-08</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Free Library of Philadelphia.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="social engagements|friends">social engagements|friends</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>London. 1 Devonshire Terrace / York Gate Regents Park</placeName>
               <date when="1846-02-07">Twenty Seventh February 1846.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Since those remote times when I had the pleasure of passing some happy hours in your society, I have heard wild legends concerning you – darkly shadowing forth the possibility of your entrance into the blessed state,<note>Fletcher married Harriet Eugenia (1815-89), daughter of Eugene Callanan of Lisbon, in 1845.</note> and furthermore of your presenting yourself in Italy, when I was there, a year ago. As you never came, I am induced to think you may possibly be in Edinburgh; and if so, allow me to present to you, one of my dearest and most valued friends, in the person of Mr. Macready. His name is not strange to you; nor will he be long, I think.</p>
<p>Mrs. Dickens begs to be cordially remembered to you.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Always Believe me / Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS | Angus Fletcher Esquire</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>