<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> THE MASTER OF THE CROWN HOTEL, ROCHESTER, 6 February 1846</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-09</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Bloomsbury Auctions online catalogue, December 2015.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="">food|family|friends|travel</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profile18Desc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Devonshire Terrace London</placeName>
               <date when="1846-02-06">Friday afternoon| Sixth February 1846</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute> Servant | Mr John Tompson<note>Thus in MS; added in another hand. John Thompson (1821-71), CD’s man-servant.</note>  </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Mr Charles Dickens sends his compliments to the Master of the Crown Hotel at Rochester, and begs to say that he wishes to secure for tomorrow and Sunday, a comfortable Private Sitting room – a bedroom for himself and Mrs Dickens – another for a young lady<note>Georgina Hogarth (1827-1917), CD’s sister-in-law.
</note> – and two more for two gentlemen<note>Douglas Jerrold and Daniel Maclise, although CD’s letter to Emile de la Rue (dated 16 February 1846) states that Maclise did not join the party, which was in celebration of CD’s birthday; see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> </note> who will accompany them.4 Also dinner for five persons<note>Added over caret.
</note> at five o’Clock tomorrow,<note>Added over caret.
</note> with Soup and Fish. Mr Dickens intends to come down by the Twelve o’Clock Gravesend Boat from Blackheath.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>