<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> CHARLES NIXON,<note>Possibly of 10 Upper Belgrave Place.</note> 22 APRIL 1846</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-02-20</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Replaces catalogue extract (aa) given in Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters </hi>12, p. 602. Text from digitised facsimile on eBay, undated.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="travel|public recognition|celebrity|Switzerland|Dombey and Son|The Battle of Life">travel|public recognition|celebrity|Switzerland|Dombey and Son|The Battle of Life</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>1 Devonshire Terrace</placeName>
               <date when="1846-04-22">Twenty Second April 1846.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute> Sir </salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I beg to say in reply to your obliging letter, that I cannot accede to the request with which the Members of the Parochial Committee2<note>The request not identified.</note>have honoured me, as aI think it very probable I may be induced to take my family to Switzerland this Summer,<note>CD left with his family for Switzerland, 31 May, staying there until he moved to Paris, 16 November.</note> and may remain there (for the more quiet execution of a literary project)<note>CD began writing <hi rend="italic">Dombey and Son</hi>, “a long book...which I could write better in retirement” (To Coutts, 22 Apr 46), in Lausanne in June. He also began there in September his Christmas Book, <hi rend="italic">The Battle of Life</hi>: “I never had to begin two stories together, before: and it is desperate work” (To Mitton, 25 Sep 46).</note> some twelve months.<hi rend="italic">a</hi><note>CD, with short visits to London, stayed abroad until his return from Paris at the end of February 1847.</note></p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am Sir | Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS | Mr. Charles Nixon</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>