<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> ADA LOVELACE,<note>Augusta Ada King, née Byron, Countess of Lovelace (1815-1852; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>); mathematician, scientist, and computer pioneer. Lovelace and CD likely met through Charles Babbage, to whom she was introduced in 1833.</note> 14 JUNE 1847</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Christie's online catalogue, July 2020.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="friends|social engagements">friends|social engagements</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Chester Place.<note>CD and his wife Catherine rented a house at 1 Chester Place, Regent’s Park, from March to June 1847; a tenant was occupying their Devonshire Terrace home. Their eldest son Charley had come down with scarlet fever at King’s College, which necessitated their early return to London; the rest of the children followed from Paris a few days later (see <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Augustus Tracey, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 5, pp. 32-33). The family had been in France since Nov 1846.</note></placeName>
               <date when="1847-06-14">Fourteenth June 1847.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Lady Lovelace.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>On Thursday next at half past Seven, I hope to break the spell.<note>CD had evidently attempted to call on Lovelace previously, and had been unsuccessful, following his letter to Lovelace on 31 Mar 1847, requesting the address of a friend living in Genoa, Sir George William Craufurd; see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 5, p. 49, and <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Ada Lovelace [?4 or 11 April 1847].</note> Many thanks for giving me another chance of doing so!</p>
<p>The | Countess of Lovelace</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>  Always Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>