<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> ADA LOVELACE,<note>Augusta Ada King, <hi rend="italic">née</hi> Byron, Countess of Lovelace (1815-1852; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>); mathematician, scientist, and computer pioneer. Lovelace and CD likely met through Charles Babbage, to whom she was introduced in 1833. CD had written a very formal letter to Lovelace on 31 Mar 1847, requesting the address of a friend living in Genoa, Sir George William Craufurd, 3rd Baronet of Kilbernie. CD wrote that he “has an interest” in an old servant of Craufurd’s (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 5, p. 49)</note> [?4 or 11 APRIL 1847] </title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-29</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Christie's online catalogue, July 2020.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="friends|social engagements">friends|social engagements</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
	<address>
	<addrLine> The | Countess of Lovelace. 
	</addrLine>
	</address>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Chester Place<note>CD and his wife Catherine rented a house at 1 Chester Place, Regent’s Park, from March to June 1847; a tenant was occupying their Devonshire Terrace home. Their eldest son Charley had come down with scarlet fever at King’s College, which necessitated their early return to London; the rest of the children followed from Paris a few days later (see To Augustus Tracey, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 5, pp. 32-33). The family had been in France since Nov 1846.</note></placeName>
               <date when="">Sunday Evening</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Lady Lovelace</salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I have, most unfortunately, someone from the country<note> Unidentified </note> dining here; and I fear I may not get rid of him in time to come round to you. I will be more than usually dull, however, and perhaps he'll go. – If I were alone, I should be really delighted to respond to your very kind note by putting myself in the Brougham and coming round, immediately</p>
<p>   In case I should not be released in an hour or so, I will repeat my call in Grosvenor Place,<note>Lady Lovelace was temporarily resident in Grosvenor Place, 1847-8.</note> on Tuesday afternoon before dinner time. Pray do not mind being out. I shall be close in your neighbourhood in any case.</p>
<p>I write in the dark – legibly, I hope</p>
<p> Always Dear Lady Lovelace</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Yours very faithfully
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>