<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MARY ELLEN THATCHER GERBINI GREVILLE,<note>Mary Ellen Thatcher Gerbini (1829-1914), daughter of Fanny Kelly; her origins are unclear. Born in Edinburgh, and lived thereafter with Kelly; she became generally known as "Miss Greville". Opinions differ as to whether she was an illegitimate daughter, possibly by the playwright and theatre manager Samuel Arnold (1774-1852), or adopted, perhaps at the behest of the clown, Joseph Grimaldi (1778-1837), whose <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> CD published (1838), and in whose welfare Kelly had taken an interest.</note> 24 DECEMBER 1847 </title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-29</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Shapero Rare Books online catalogue, March 2020.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="charity|theatre">charity|theatre</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
		<address>
		<addrLine> Miss Greville
		</addrLine>
		</address>
               <placeName> Devonshire Terrace

</placeName>
               <date when="1847-12-24">Friday Twenty Fourth December</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Miss Greville</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am extremely sorry for the cause of Miss Kelly’s<note>Frances Maria (Fanny) Kelly (1790-1882; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), well-known actress and singer; retired from Drury Lane 1835; also acted in monologues at the Strand 1833-9. Under the Duke of Devonshire's patronage, she built her own theatre, the Royalty, at 73 Dean St, Soho Square, opened 1840; it was used for plays, operas, and monologues, as well as for Miss Kelly's dramatic school, and was sometimes hired by amateurs, including CD, who used it to stage Every Man in His Humour in October 1845. CD also arranged benefit performances at the theatre for Miss Kelly in December 1845 and July 1847; see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, pp. 448-9, 454-5, and 482-3, and Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 5, pp. 85, 114, 146. CD had also arranged play readings for his amateur company at Miss Kelly's theatre on 16 Nov 1847; see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 5, p. 195. See also Robert C. Hanna, "Frances Maria Kelly, Charles Dickens, and Miss Kelly's Theatre and Dramatic School", Dickensian 114 (2018): 278-93.</note> non-appearance to-day. Pray assure her that I shall be happy to see her any morning in the week after next, between ten and one – except on the 6th or 7th<note>No full stop in MS. In Alan Wilson's unpublished book, <hi rend="italic">Divine Plain Face: The Story of Fanny Kelly</hi> (1986), he quotes from a letter Miss Kelly wrote in Dec 1847 from her new residence in Moscow Road, Bayswater (having relocated there from Dean Street), asking the unidentified recipient to send “some honest and experienced person to fasten the slate on the roof of the Theatre.” Presumably Miss Kelly had requested permission to call on CD at his home, in order to request additional financial assistance. Knowing that CD was still renting her theatre, she could have expected him to be sympathetic to her plight; however, no payment to Kelly appears in CD's bank account in Jan 1848 (MS Messrs Coutts). There was a payment of £10 on 4 March 1848, probably for hire of her theatre.</note></p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>