<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To THOMAS WEBSTER,<note>Thomas Webster (1800-86), painter, particularly of children. ARA 1840; RA 1846. Exhibited frequently; in the RA exhibition 1847 his painting Instruction was described as ‘a little gem . . . one of the boasts of the year’ (Literary Gazette, 5 June).</note> 7 April 1848</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Emily Bell</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-01-02</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Stephen Weekes </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="visual arts|Nicholas Nickleby|Dombey and Son">visual arts|Nicholas Nickleby|Dombey and Son</interp>
            </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>Seventh April 1848.
               <placeName>DEVONSHIRE TERRACE</placeName>
               <date when="1848-04-07">1848-04-07</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>If you will kindly let me know in what amount I stand indebted to you,<note>CD purchased the brimstone and treacle scene from <hi rend="italic">Nicholas Nickleby</hi>, which Webster painted as frontispiece for the Cheap edition; see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 5, p. 203. The companion picture from <hi rend="italic">Dombey</hi>, mentioned in this letter, has not been found.</note> I shall be happy to discharge the pecuniary part of my obligation.</p>
<p>I hope to send you, in the course of a week or so, the completed Dombey wherein you will find, at your leisure, that other subject for the companion picture.</p>
<p>Accept my best thanks for the enduring pleasure you have given me, and believe me</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
Very faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>