<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> CHARLES GEACH,<note>Charles Geach (1808-54), junior clerk at the Bank of England in London and Birmingham; 1836 appointed manager of the newly-established Birmingham and Midland Bank. MP for Coventry, 1851-54. Involved in commercial and manufacturing enterprises, and increasingly with railway companies.</note> 8 JUNE 1849</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-03</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Rose Geach.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="friends">friends</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
	<address>
	<addrLine> Charles Geach Esquire | Birmingham and Midland Bank | Birmingham.
	</addrLine>
	</address>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Devonshire Terrace. </placeName>
               <date when="1849-06-08">Eighth June 1849</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Both Mrs. Dickens and I are exceedingly indebted to you for your kind letter, and wish it were in our power to accept your hospitable invitation, which it would give us great pleasure to do. But we have arranged with some friends to be down at the Seaside all August and September, and we are, therefore, not at our own disposal.</p>
<p>I regret very much not to have seen you when you were last in town, and can assure you that I shall be really happy to renew and improve our acquaintance.<note>CD presumably met Geach in 1848, when the Amateur Company acted in Birmingham, 6 and 27 June. CD was in Bonchurch, Isle of Wight, from late July to the end of September 1849.</note> Mrs. Dickens begs me to send you her remembrances.</p>
<p>Charles Geach Esquire

</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>My Dear Sir|  Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>