<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MISS ROSS,<note>Either Georgina or her younger sister Thomasina. Their brother Charles Ross was a parliamentary reporter on <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> and a friend of CD’s since 1832; CD became friendly with the whole family. Thomasina was an accomplished linguist, and contributed eight papers to <hi rend="italic">Household Words</hi> between 1850 and 1851. In 1852 the Earl of Carlisle applied to Lord John Russell, then Prime Minister, for a Civil List pension in recognition of Thomasina Ross’s literary labours; the appeal succeeded three years later. See William J. Carlton, 'Dickens and the Ross Family', <hi rend="italic">Dickensian</hi> 51 (1955): 58-66.</note> 1 APRIL 1850</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-06</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Leslie Hindman Auctioneers online catalogue, August 2015.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="charity|friends">charity|friends</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Devonshire Terrace</placeName>
               <date when="1850-04-01">First April 1850.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Miss Ross</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am very sorry that I cannot be of any assistance to you in the matter you confide to me. Nor need I hesitate, in the same confidence, to tell you why. It is not a month, since I communicated with Lord John Russell<note>Lord John Russell (1792-1878; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), Prime minister 1846-52, author and friend of CD.</note> on the subject of a small pension for Mr Poole<note>John Poole (1785/6-1872; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), playwright, author of the highly successful Paul Pry (1825) and very popular in the days of CD’s youth. In the mid-1840s he fell on hard times and relied on the kindness of CD, John Forster and Thomas Noon Talfourd. They negotiated grants to him from the Royal Literary Fund, and in 1847 CD donated to him some of the proceeds of his amateur theatrical performances at Liverpool and Manchester. See letters from CD to Russell on Poole’s behalf, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6 pp. 232-3 and pp. 239-40. Poole was awarded a Civil List pension of £100 p.a.</note>, who has no means of existence and is quite unable to write. The question is still pending, but Lord John immediately assisted him from another public source, and that in so handsome a manner that I should feel it (as I am sure you will understand<note>A small tear has removed the final "d".</note> on this explanation) indelicate and obtrusive, to bring another such application under his notice.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>With all good wishes, Believe me| Faithfully yours 
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>