<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> <hi rend="italic">To</hi> MISS GEORGINA HOGARTH, 30 MAY 1848</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-11</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS State University of New York, Buffalo.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="">friends|family</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>OFFICE OF HOUSEHOLD WORDS</placeName>
               <date when="1850-08-23">Friday Twenty Third August 1850</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Georgy.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Forster<note>John Forster (1812-76; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), historian and man of letters, CD's closest friend and biographer.</note> don’t come tomorrow,<note>CD was staying in Broadstairs, with occasional trips to London on business; he was returning to Broadstairs on 24 Aug.</note> having the Narrative<note>The <hi rend="italic">Household Narrative of Current Events</hi> (a monthly supplement to Household Words), which Forster helped to compile and for which he wrote leaders: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6, p. 18n.</note> to attend to. Neither does Fred. I am not sure but Stone may. I shall come by the Ramsgate boat, and be put ashore at Broadstairs. All well, and Kate most blooming.<note>Catherine had given birth to a daughter, Dora Annie, 16 Aug.</note> </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Ever affectionately | Loves to all the Darlings. 
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>