<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> ALBERT SMITH,<note>Albert Smith (1816-60; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), author and entertainer: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 8n.</note> [JULY-DECEMBER 1851]</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-12</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="">health|social engagements</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName></placeName>
               <date when="1851-04-21">1851-04-21</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Summary and extract in Cuthbert Bede, “Unpublished Anecdotes of Charles Lamb, Douglas Jerrold and Charles Dickens”, <hi rend="italic">London Sketch- Book</hi>, I, iv (April, 1874), pp. 19-22; addressed Albert Smith, undated. <hi rend="italic">Date</hi>: mention of the Crystal Palace suggests that this was written during the year of the Great Exhibition and after CD mentions his visit in a letter to Mrs Watson, 11 July 1851.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Excusing himself, on the ground that he had a severe cold, CD described the gathering and preparation for a sneeze, </hi>and,<hi rend="italic"> in imagery drawn from the Crystal Palace, the laying on of the complete series of waterworks, upper and lower basins, and the grand finale of the accomplished sneeze.</hi><note>CD likens his sneeze to the great fountain by Osler, Follett &amp; Clarkson, a centrepiece of the Great Exhibition in Hyde Park, May-Sep 51. The 27-foot fountain featured a main water spout, as well as smaller jets lower down, from which water streamed into an upper and lower basin. CD visited the Crystal Palace twice; he specifically recalled the Osler fountain: <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Mrs Watson, 11 July, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6, p. 428. CD had a severe cold on 11 July (To Wills, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6, p. 430) and again on 31 Oct (<hi rend="italic">To</hi> Watson, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6 , pp. 532-3).</note> </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>