<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> F. O. WARD,<note>Frederick Oldfield Ward (?1815-77), writer on sanitary subjects: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 86n.</note> 19 JANUARY 1852</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Phillip Pirages.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="social issues|Bleak House|friends">social issues|Bleak House|friends</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>185
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House

</placeName>
               <date when="1852-01-19">Monday Nineteenth January | 1852.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>My Dear Ward. I seem to be under a kind of spell when you propose anything. I am engaged on Wednesday—with my new book<note><hi rend="italic">Bleak House</hi> (No. I published 28 Feb).</note> in the day, and to dine at Bayswater with Egg the Painter,<note>Augustus Leopold Egg (1816-63; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), artist: see Pilgrim Letters 5, p. 113n.</note> in the evening. But I will get my Sub Editor Mr. Wills to see the invention<note>Not identified. Ward was particularly concerned with drainage for London and supported Sir Joseph Bazalgette: see Stephen Halliday, <hi rend="italic">The Great Stink of London: Sir Joseph Bazalgette and the Cleansing of the Victorian Metropolis</hi>, Stroud, Glos, 1999.</note> with a view to some account of it in Household Words,<note>No account of Ward or his invention appears in Household Words during the next year, though articles by Henry Morley (“A Foe under Foot”, <hi rend="italic">Household Words</hi>, 11 Dec 52, VI, 289-92) and by Wills (“Clear Water and Dirty Water”, <hi rend="italic">Household Words</hi>, 5 Feb 53, VI, 496-7) both concern sanitation.</note> and (as he knows Chadwick)<note>Edwin Chadwick (1800-90; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), social reformer. CD supported his efforts for sanitary reform.</note> will propose to him to be at the Board of Health<note>The General Board of Health, established 1848, with Chadwick as Chairman; its statutory life ended, July 54. The new Board, established Aug 54, was chaired by Benjamin Hall (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, pp. 384<hi rend="italic">nn</hi>, 400<hi rend="italic">nn</hi>).</note> at the hour you appoint. </p>
<p>F. O. Ward Esquire.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CD</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>