<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> THE GOVERNORS OF THE FOUNDLING HOSPITAL,<note>The Foundling Hospital, Guilford St, now the Thomas Coram Foundation for Children: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 2, p. 34n. CD and Wills described the Hospital and its work in 'Received, a Blank Child', <hi rend="italic">Household Words</hi> 7 (19 March 1853): 49-53.</note> 9 JULY 1852</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-08</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Bloomsbury Auctions online catalogue, March 2015.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="Urania Cottage|charity<">Urania Cottage|charity</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House, Tavistock Square

</placeName>
               <date when="1852-07-09">Friday Ninth July 1852.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I beg to state to the Governors of the Foundling Hospital that I have read the printed paper describing the qualifications they require in their Matron; and that I very earnestly and strongly recommend Mrs Morson<note>Georgiana Morson (née Collin, ?1817-1880), matron of Urania Cottage 1849-54. See Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6, pp. 703 and 710; CD was ‘very sorry to hear’ that Mrs Morson was making this application, which was not successful.</note> to their favorable consideration.</p>
<p>
For upwards of three years, I have had constant opportunities of observing Mrs Morson’s capacity for the administration of such an office.<note>For CD’s account of Urania Cottage, see his article 'Home for Homeless Women', <hi rend="italic">Household Words</hi> 7 (23 April 1853): 169-75. See also Jenny Hartley, <hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens and the House of Fallen Women</hi> (2009).</note> She has been, during that time the principal directress of an establishment for the reclamation and training of young women, which is maintained by the munificence of Miss Burdett Coutts<note>Angela Georgina Burdett Coutts (1814-1906; <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), philanthropist and long-standing friend of CD, with whom she collaborated on Urania Cottage and other social work projects.</note>, and with the management of which I am intimately associated. She is a lady of great discretion, of remarkable sweetness of temper, and has a power of uniting firmness with conciliation in a very remarkable and uncommon manner. I have never known her to make a mistake even under circumstances of great difficulty, and I have invariably found that those under her care have become attached to her. She is accustomed to method, order, punctuality, and to a habit of sound and judicious observation. I would entrust her, myself, with the duties to which she now aspires, in preference to any lady I have ever seen in a similar capacity.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>