<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MAJOR LAKE<note>Major Edward John Lake (1823-77; <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), army officer, commissioned in Bengal Engineers 1840; saw active service in the Punjab. Between 1852 and 1854 he was in England on furlough.</note>, 24 APRIL 1853</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile on eBay August 2016.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="social engagements|travel">social engagements|travel</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
	<address>
	<addrLine>Major Lake, | 9 Charles Street, | St James’s
	</addrLine>
	</address>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House</placeName>
               <date when="1853-04-24">Twenty Fourth April, 1853.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>My difficulty about Friday, is, that I am not sure when my Scotch friend<note>CD’s old friend John Thomson Gordon (1813-65), Sheriff of Midlothian, was staying with him at this time; see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 64 and n; also pp. 65, 71. For further information on Gordon see Paul Schlicke and William F Long, 'Dickens’s Second-Best Scottish Friend: John Thomson Gordon 1813-1865,' <hi rend="italic">Dickensian</hi> 111.3 (2015): 257- 64.</note> departs for Edinburgh, but I rather think he will not go until Saturday at the earliest. Therefore I am with-held from making any engagement, as we go wildly to theatres and other public places, and I am bound to keep within call – like a Surgeon. I think our only course is, to trust to our better fortune – Autumn – and India!  Or possibly you may find yourself at Boulogne in the course of the Summer, when I should be very happy to see you there. If I can get a good house, I purpose passing the whole summer in that place.</p>
<p>Major Lake.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Very faithfully yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>