<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> W. W. F. DE CERJAT,<note>William Woodley Frederick de Cerjat (d. 1869), member of an old Vaudois family. Resident at Lausanne, where CD came to know him as a friend in 1846.</note> 16 JANUARY 1854</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-12</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Lehigh University Special Collections, Bethlehem, PA. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id=""> A Christmas Carol|Queen Victoria|politics|social|issues|friends|travel|Italy|Household Words|France|food|family|railway|public readings|Switzerland
</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
	<address>William W. F. De Cerjat Esqre | Elysée | Lausanne | Switzerland.
	</address>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House, London </placeName>
               <date when="1854-01-16"> Monday Sixteenth January 1854</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>My Dear Cerjat. Guilty. The accused pleads guilty, but throws himself upon the mercy of the Court.<note>Clearly CD had not written to Cerjat during his Italian travels (next note), though he had seen him 16 Oct when briefly in Lausanne on his journey.</note> He humbly represents that his usual hour for getting up, in the course of his travels,<note>CD travelled in Switzerland and Italy, 10 Oct-11 Dec 53: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7. His companions were Wilkie Collins (see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6, p. 310n) and the artist Augustus Egg (see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 5, p. 113n).</note> was three o’Clock in the morning, and his usual hour for going to bed, nine or ten the next night. That the places in which he chiefly deviated from these rules of hardship, were Rome and Venice;<note>CD arrived in Rome, 12 Nov, and in Venice, 24 Nov.</note> and that at those cities of Fame he shut himself up in solitude, and wrote Christmas papers for the incomparable publication known as Household Words.<note>In Rome CD wrote “The Schoolboy's Story” and in Venice, “Nobody’s Story”, <hi rend="italic">Household Words</hi>, Extra Christmas No. 1853, 1-5, 34-6.</note> That his correspondence at all times, arising out of the business of the said Household Words alone, was very heavy. That his offence, though undoubtedly committed, was unavoidable, and that a nominal punishment will meet the justice of the case.</p>

<p>
We had only three bad days out of the whole time. After Naples,<note>CD arrived in Naples, 4 Nov, staying about a week.</note> which was very hot, we had very cold, clear, bright weather.When we got to Chamounix, we found the greater part of the Inns shut up and the people gone – no visitors whatsoever – and plenty of snow.<note>CD stayed in Chamounix, 19-21 Oct: see also <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Mrs CD, 20 &amp; 21 Oct 53, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> , p. 168.</note> These were the very best circumstances under which to see the place, and we stayed a couple of days at the Hotel de Londres (hastily re-furbished for our entertainment) and climbed through the snow to the Mer de Glace,<note>The great glacier, terminating in the Glacier du Bois; the source of the river Arveron (modern Arve) in the valley of Chamounix. CD had been there in 1846: see PIlgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, pp. 594-5. The excursion from Chamounix took 21⁄2 hours by mule and 2 hours back. The “old” hotel (i.e. where they stayed in 1846) was the Hotel de la Grande Maison: PIlgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 618n.</note> and thoroughly enjoyed it. Then we went, in Mule procession (I walking) to the old hotel at Martigny, where Collins was ill, and I suppose I bored Egg to death by talking all the evening about the time when you and I were there together. Naples (a place always painful to me, in the intense degradation of the people)<note>In 1845 CD had found the “condition of the common people” in Naples “abject and shocking” (<hi rend="italic"> To</hi> Forster, [11 Feb 45] and [?22 Feb 45], Pilgrim <hi rend="italic"> Letters</hi> 4, pp. 266 &amp; 271).</note> seems to have only three classes of inhabitants left in it – priests, soldiers (standing army one hundred thousand strong) and spies.<note>For CD’s gloom about the state of Naples, see <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Forster, [?4 Dec 53], Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 222 &amp; <hi rend="italic">n</hi>.</note> Of Maccaroni we ate very considerable quantities everywhere; also, for the benefit of Italy, we took our share of every description of Wine.At Naples I found Layard the Nineveh Traveller,<note>Austen Henry Layard (1817-94; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), archaeologist and radical politician: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6, p. 555n. He had published <hi rend="italic">Nineveh and Babylon</hi>, on his second series of excavations, in Summer 53.</note> who is a friend of mine and an admirable fellow; so we fraternised and went up Vesuvius together,<note>They “ascended Vesuvius in the Sunlight, and came down in the Moonlight, very merrily” (<hi rend="italic">To</hi> Miss Coutts, <note>In fact, the beatification (declaring “Blessed”), not the canonisation (declaring a “Saint”) of Giovanni Grande, 13 Nov 53. Grande (1546-1600), who worked in hospitals and prisons, punning on his Spanish surname, called himself the “Grande Pecador” – the “Great Sinner”: see also <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Hogarth, 13 Nov 53, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 192 &amp; <hi rend="italic">n</hi>.</note> Nov 53, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 189). CD had previously climbed Vesuvius, with Catherine Dickens and Georgina, Hogarth 21 Feb 45: <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Mitton, 17 &amp; 22 Feb 45, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, pp. 269-71.</note> and ate more Maccaroni and drank more Wine. At Rome, the day after our arrival, they were making a Saint at St. Peters:13 on which occasion I was surprised to find what an immense number of pounds of wax candles it takes to make the regular, genuine article. From Turin to Paris, over the Mont Cenis, we made only one journey.<note>CD left Turin, 6 Dec 53; here he gives Friday 9 Dec as the date of his Paris arrival: see also <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Regnier, [10 Dec 53], Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 225<hi rend="italic">hn</hi>.</note> The Rhone being frozen and foggy was not to be navigated, so we posted from Lyons to Chalons<note>The Rhone and the Saône meet at Lyons; Chalon is on the Saône (as CD knew: Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 223).</note> – and everybody else was doing the like – and there were no horses to be got – and we were stranded at midnight in amazing little cabarets, with nothing worth mentioning to eat in them, except the iron stove – which was rusty, and the billiard table – which was musty. We left Turin on a Tuesday evening, and arrived in Paris on the Friday evening; where I found my son Charley hot – or I should rather say, cold – from Germany,<note>Charley, returning home for Christmas, was spending a year in Leipzig to improve his German and business experience. CD arranged for them to meet in Paris and travel on to London (<hi rend="italic">To</hi> CD Jnr, 25 Nov 53, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 208).</note> with his arms and legs so grown out of his coat and trousers that I was ashamed of him, and was reduced to the necessity of taking him, under cover of night, to a ready made establishment in the Palais Royal, where they put him into balloon-waisted pantaloons and increased my confusion. Leaving Calais on the evening of Sunday the 10th. of December,<note>Sunday was 11 Dec; rapid travel presumably caused confusion, since To <hi rend="italic">Regnier</hi>, [10 Dec 53], was misdated at the time. CD started from Paris on the Sunday morning.</note> fact of<note>“fact of” written above caret.</note> distinguished author’s being aboard was telegraphed to Dover, whereupon authorities of Dover Railway detained Train to London for distinguished author’s arrival – rather to the exasperation of British public. D. A. arrived home between 10 and 11 that night thankful, and found all well and happy.
</p>
<p>I think you see the Times, and if so you will have seen a very graceful and good account of the Birmingham readings.<note>CD’s three readings on behalf of the Birmingham and Midland Institute, 27, 29 and 30 Dec 53. Reported in <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 2 Jan; Catherine was presented with a “silver flower-stand” on 31 Dec (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 250nn). See also CD’s account of the third reading (of the Carol) specifically for working men: <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Mrs Watson, 13 Jan 54, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, pp. 243-4.</note> It was the most remarkable scene that England could produce I think, in the way of a vast, intelligent assemblage, and the success was  most wonderful and prodigious – perfectly overwhelming and astounding altogether. They wound up by giving my wife a piece of Plate, having given me one before; and when you come to dine here (may it be soon!) it shall be duly displayed in the centre of the table.
</p>
<p>Tell Mrs. Cerjat,<note>Maria, daughter of Peter Holmes of Peterville, Co. Tipperary.</note> to whom my love and all our loves, that I have highly excited them at home here by giving them an account in detail of all your daughters;<note>Maria, daughter of Peter Holmes of Peterville, Co. Tipperary.Cerjat had five daughters: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 165n.</note> further, that the<note>“y” crossed out after “the”.</note> way in which Catherine and Georgina have questioned and crossquestioned me about you all, notwithstanding, is maddening. Mrs. Watson<note>The Hon. Mrs Watson, <hi rend="italic">née</hi> Lavinia Jane Quin (1816-88): see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 4, p. 574n. Her husband, the Hon. Richard Watson, had died, 24 July 52.</note> has been obliged to pass her Christmas at Brighton alone with her younger children, in consequence of her two eldest boys coming home to Rockingham from school, with the hooping cough.<note>“hooping” thus in original (rather than "whooping"). As well as George (b. 1841), Edward Spencer (b. 1843), and Mary Georgiana (b. 1845) – “the jolly boys, and the calm little girl”, CD called them (<hi rend="italic">To</hi> Mrs Watson, 24 Jan 51, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6, p. 266) – a daughter, Lavinia Grace, had been born posthumously, Feb 53. The boys were both at Eton.</note> The quarantine expires to day, however, and she dines here, on her way back into Northamptonshire, tomorrow.<note>Mrs Watson clearly confirmed, in reply to CD's letter of 13 Jan (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 244), that she would stay two nights in London and dine with the Dickenses on 17 Jan, on her way home to Rockingham Castle.</note> There is great talk about Prince Albert’s interference in foreign politics, and the Queen is supposed to be undecided whether to open Parliament in person or not: fearing his present unpopularity.<note>The Prince was widely believed to exert an undue influence over his wife and to favour pro-Prussian and pro-Austrian policies. In the agitation over the Eastern Question, late 53-early 54, when Anglo-French support for Turkey against Russian aggression culminated in the declaration of war, Mar 54, popular feeling ran high against Albert. The Prince himself wrote, <note>The Preston weavers had been on strike for over 20 weeks. CD visited Preston in late January and wrote “On Strike”, <hi rend="italic">Household Words</hi>, 11 Feb 54, VIII, 555, later incorporating some of his observations in <hi rend="italic">Hard Times</hi>.</note> Dec 53, that “treachery is the cry, and, guided by a friendly hand, the whole press has for the last week made ‘a dead set at the Prince’...My unconstitutional position, correspondence with Foreign Courts, dislike to Palmerston...are depicted as the causes of the decline of the State, the Constitution, and the nation” (quoted in Theodore Martin, <hi rend="italic">The Life of His Royal Highness The Prince Consort</hi>, 1876, II, 535; see further ch. L). The Queen opened Parliament in person, 31 Jan 54; en route, “hisses were occasionally heard, but they were at once drowned amid the general cheering” (Household Narrative [1854], p. 25).</note> The sad affair of the Preston strike remains unsettled,<note>The Preston weavers had been on strike for over 20 weeks. CD visited Preston in late January and wrote “On Strike”, Household Words, 11 Feb 54, VIII, 555, later incorporating some of his observations in Hard Times.</note> and I hear on strong authority that, if that were settled, the Manchester people are prepared to strike next.<note>There was a serious strike by the Manchester mill-workers the following year.</note> Provisions very dear, but the people very temperate and quiet in general. So ends this jumble – which looks like the index to a chapter in a book,<note>CD refers to the convention of providing a summary of a chapter at its head or on the contents page.</note> I find when I read it over.
</p>


         <closer>
            <salute>Ever My Dear Cerjat. Heartily Your friend CHARLES DICKENS
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>