<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MESSRS BANTING AND SONS,<note>William Banting &amp; Sons, 9 Park Lane, Grosvenor Square and 27 St James’s, Piccadilly, undertakers.</note> 3 NOVEMBER 1855</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-15</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Kotte Autographs, Germany.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="friends">friends</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName></placeName>
               <date when="1855-11-03">1855-11-03</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Mr. Charles Dickens will be punctual in his attendance on the mournful occasion<note>Dr William Brown, husband of Miss Coutts’s companion, Hannah (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Meredith), had died suddenly, 23 Oct, when at Montpellier with Miss Coutts and his wife. CD, then staying in Paris, undertook the arrangements for Dr Brown’s burial at St Stephen’s, Rochester Row (7 Nov), returning to London for the purpose (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, pp. 727-35 &amp; nn). CD’s is a formal response to the firm after formal notification.</note> to which the letter of Messrs. Banting and Sons refers.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>