<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MR SMYTH,<note> Unidentified </note> 19 SEPTEMBER 1855</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-30</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Bloomsbury Auctions online catalogue, March 2017.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="celebrity|public readings|Little Dorrit">celebrity|public readings|Little Dorrit</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Folkestone, Kent.</placeName>
               <date when="1855-09-19">Wednesday Nineteenth September | 1855.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>Mr Charles Dickens presents his compliments to Mr Smyth, and begs to say he cannot have the pleasure of complying with the request preferred in that gentleman’s note. He is very busily engaged at present with his own pursuits – will visit Sheffield at considerable inconvenience<note>CD had agreed to read <hi rend="italic">A Christmas Carol</hi> on 22 December at Sheffield – an “old” promise (see <hi rend="italic">To</hi> John Forster, 16 September 1855, in Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 701), although he did not ultimately do so.</note>  ­– and has his arrangements made for immediately returning to the avocations that now engross his attention.<note>CD was just beginning to write the third monthly number of <hi rend="italic">Little Dorrit</hi> (Bk I, Chs 9-11).</note></p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>