<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> GEORGE [?DARLING],<note>Unidentified. Name uncertain; “Darling” possible.</note> 22 APRIL 1857</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Alexautographs catalogue, 2010.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="domestic issues|celebrity">domestic issues|celebrity</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House, London</placeName>
               <date when="1857-04-22">Twenty Second April 1857 </date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>My absence from London<note>CD was in Gravesend, 7-15 Apr, to keep “an eye on the little repairs” at Gad’s Hill (<hi rend="italic">To</hi> Miss Coutts, 9 Apr; Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi~> 8, p. 310). He was clearing off accumulated correspondence on his return to London.</note> has prevented my returning an earlier reply to your letter, and sending back your Manuscript with thanks. I can hardly be expected to recognize the necessity of the question propounded at your Debating Society, as I may be reasonably supposed to have settled it very conclusively in my own mind. But it is extremely agreeable and gratifying to me to have so earnest a champion as yourself and to find the generous order of youth expressing itself so well, and with so strong a love of what is good and true.</p>
<p> Mr. George [?Darling] Junr.

</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>