<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To H.M. CUSTOMS &amp; EXCISE, 8 APRIL 1857</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-11</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Skinner Auction House catalogue, 2005.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="publishing|David Copperfield|Pickwick Papers|Germany">publishing|David Copperfield|Pickwick Papers|Germany</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House London </placeName>
               <date when="1857-04-08">Eighth April, 1857</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I beg to state that I give my free consent, on the solicitation of Mr. King of St. Michael’s Hill, Bristol,<note>Frederick A. King, Accountant and Agent for the Medical, Legal and General and the New Equitable Life Assurance Societies, 16 St Michael’s Hill.</note> to the admission into this country of one copy of a Leipzig reprint of David Copperfield, and one copy of a Leipzig reprint of Pickwick<note>The Tauchnitz  “Collection of British Authors”in English, was published in Leipzig for continental circulation only, and prohibited from import into England or any British colony. Tauchnitz had published The Pickwick Papers in 1841 and <hi rend="italic">David Copperfield</hi> in 1849-50.</note> (I being the author of both books) brought over by a German<note>Written above caret.</note> passenger<note> Unidentified </note> from Manilla<note>Written above caret after “Germany” deleted.</note> in the Hamburg ship Martaban.<note>The Hamburg-registered, British-built brigantine <hi rend="italic">Martaban</hi> sailed regularly between Auckland and Liverpool; it left Singapore, bound for England, 28 Feb 57.</note>

</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>