<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> JOHN THOMPSON,<note>John Thompson (1822-71), CD’s trusted servant, c. 1841-67; he acted as dresser, secretary, and coachman. Stole money from CD's cash box, Nov 1866 (see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 11, pp. 262, 268), but not dismissed outright; CD eventually facilitated his finding employment as a tobacconist.</note> 15 AUGUST 1857</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-28</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile on eBay, January 2011.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="domestic issues|servants">domestic issues|servants</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Gad’s Hill Place</placeName>
               <date when="1857-08-18">Saturday Fifteenth August, 1857<note>Address and date at foot of letter.</note></date>
            </dateline>
            <salute></salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am particularly anxious, John, that Mr.Austin<note>Henry Austin (?1812-61), architect and civil engineer; married Letitia Dickens 1837. See Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 1, p. 21n.</note> should have the enclosed letter<note>To Henry Austin, 15 Aug. The water supply at Gad’s Hill was a constant problem: in June the well ran dry and though now CD wrote to Austin that “we have got a famous spring”, the well needed to be dug 217 ft deep and the water was raised by a horse-driven pump (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 8, p. 411, n.1).</note> to night or early tomorrow morning. It relates to the well here. We have found at last a great spring of water. I want you to take the letter down to him. Go to Ealing by the Railroad, and you will find his house about half a mile from the station. If you find him at home and get an answer, send it, or bring it, down here, any time tomorrow (Sunday.)</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>