<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To HENRY WHITWORTH JONES, 2 JANUARY 1857</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-21</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p> MS Private. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="theatre">theatre</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House</placeName>
               <date when="1857-01-02">Second January 1857</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Mr. Whitworth</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>It was reported to me some time ago, that you had goodnaturedly declared you would like to “go on” in the Play,<note><hi rend="italic">The Frozen Deep</hi> by Wilkie Collins; performed in Jan 57 at Tavistock House: see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 8.</note> for the fun of being in it. If this should be really so, and you do not object to become a Mute Seaman,<note>As one of the crews of the <hi rend="italic">Sea Mew and Wanderer</hi>, iced-in in the Arctic Regions, in Act II: see also <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Jones, 12 June.</note> “an eligible opportunity now offers”.<note>Imitating newspaper advertisements, for vacancies in clerical and professional employment.</note> A Seaman is summoned to Sheffield,<note>Edward Hogarth, Catherine’s youngest brother, due to play Bateson; employed in a business house in Sheffield threatened by failure: <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Thomas Hankey, 11 Dec 57, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 8, p. 491.</note> and another Seaman (the speechless one) is ill.<note> Unidentified </note> We rehearse tonight at 1⁄4 before 8, for the last time before the Dress Rehearsal on Monday.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Faithfully Yours always
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CD</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>