<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> FREDERIC OUVRY,<note>Frederic Ouvry (1814-81) CD’s solicitor from 1856.</note>, 17 MAY 1858

</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Hospitalfield Arts Centre.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="charity|legal matters">charity|legal matters</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House</placeName>
               <date when="1858-05-17">Seventeenth May 1858</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>You will perceive from the enclosed letter of the Honorary Solicitor to the Guild<note>Mr Wordsworth, Honorary Solicitor for the Guild of Literature and Art, a self-help scheme for writers and artists, founded by CD and his friends in 1851. See To Patrick Allan-Fraser 19 April 1858.</note> that under the English law we must apply to Parliament for leave to amend our Act, and that we cannot even register a Petition having that object, until next November.<note>CD proposed that Ouvry seek an amendment to the 1854 Literary and Scientific Institutions Act (which incorporated the Guild of Literature and Art), so as to enable the organisation to accept a gift of Hawkesbury Hall in Warwickshire, from Patrick Allan-Fraser (1813-90). See To Ouvry, [?10 May 1858], Pilgrim Letters 8, p. 562. See also Michael Slater, "Munificence Declined: New Letters about the Guild of Literature and Art", Dickensian 111.1 (2015): 34-41.</note></p>
<p>The delay is excessively unpalatable and irksome to me; but I fear it is [           ]<note>Letter torn; words missing.</note> it and there is no possible hope of [      ]<note>Letter torn; words missing.
</note> at any earlier moment.</p>
<p>Frederic Ouvry Esquire</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Believe me ever|Very faithfully yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>