<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> ROBERT DRAKE,<note>Robert Drake, of the Chatham and Rochester Mechanics’ Institution; CD was the President.</note> 21 JANUARY 1858</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-28</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Huntington Library.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="public readings|public recognition|celebrity">public readings|public recognition|celebrity</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House, London, W.C. </placeName>
               <date when="1858-01-21"> Twenty First January 1858</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I find your note on returning from Bristol<note>Where CD read, 19 Jan.</note> after two or three days absence. If you will send the sheet to me here, I will sign it and lose no time in returning it. I don’t very clearly see what the Chatham Mechanics’ Institution has to do with the matter of the Princess Royal’s marriage;<note>Princess Victoria Adelaide Mary Louise (1840-1901; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), the Princess Royal, eldest child of Queen Victoria, married (25 Jan 58) Prince Frederick William of Prussia. Princess Victoria was later crown princess (1861) and Empress of Germany during Frederick’s brief reign (Mar-June 1888)</note> but the Society of Arts<note>The Society’s full title was The Society for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufactures and Commerce. Princess Victoria in Germany encouraged the industrial arts and established the Berlin Industrial Art Museum, 1881.</note> is so very learned in all manner of approaches to her august father,<note> Prince Albert. </note> that I have no doubt it is master of the subject.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Robert Drake Esquire.| Dear Sir | Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>