<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> WILLIAM BOXALL,<note>Sir William Boxall (1800-79; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), portrait-painter and museum director. See Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 6, p. 249n, for CD’s remarks on Boxall’s unfinished portrait of him in 1850.</note> 18 MAY 1858</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-09</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS private</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="social engagements|visual arts">social engagements|visual arts</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>TAVISTOCK HOUSE,

TAVISTOCK SQUARE,

LONDON. W.C</placeName>
               <date when="1858-05-18">Tuesday Eighteenth May, 1858</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Boxall,</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>You know that nothing but dire necessity would keep me away from your pleasant little dinner today. I could not possibly foresee the occasion of my absence, and I cannot possibly set it aside. If you knew how sorry I am, you would be half as sorry for me as I am for myself.<note>CD had previously written to William Boxall on 10 May to suggest 'Monday or Tuesday of next week' for the dinner with artist friends, see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 8, p. 561 and n. CD subsequently wrote to Captain E.E. Morgan (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 8, p. 566; (?20-22 May 1858): “All your artist friends are flourishing. I dined with a dozen of them last Tuesday, and they all smelt horribly of oil and varnish”.</note></p>
<p>W. Boxall Esquire.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Faithfully Yours always
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>