<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> PATRICK ALLAN-FRASER,<note>Patrick Allan-Fraser (1813-1890; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), artist and architect. Born Patrick Allan, son of an Arbroath stocking weaver; successively, house painter and artist; assumed additional name of Fraser 1851, after marrying in 1843 heiress of nearby estate of Hospitalfield. Devoted himself to managing his wife's estate and collecting works of art. Under his Will formed a Trust (1) to maintain Hospitalfield as an Art College for young students, and (2) to assist aged and infirm professional men, including specifically 'painters, sculptors or literary men'.</note> 3 MAY 1858</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-09</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Hospitalfield Arts Centre.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="charity|legal matters">charity|legal matters</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
	<address>Patrick Allan Fraser Esquire, Hospitalfield, Arbroath.
	<addrLine>
	</addrLine>
	</address>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Tavistock House</placeName>
               <date when="1858-05-03">Monday Third May 1858</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I have heard from Mr Ouvry<note>Frederic Ouvry (1814-81), CD's solicitor from 1856.</note> the Guild Solicitor, who is now (I believe) in communication with your Solicitor. It seems that our Act of Parliament<note>The Private Act to incorporate the Guild of Literature and Art was passed on 2 June 1854.</note> does not give us the power of holding your most generous gift,<note>CD proposed that Ouvry seek an amendment of the Act of Parliament incorporating the Guild of Literature and Art, to enable the Guild to accept a gift of land from Allan-Fraser. See To Ouvry, [?10 May 1858], Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 8, p. 562. See also Michael Slater, "Munificence Declined: New Letters about the Guild of Literature and Art", Dickensian 111.1 (2015): 34-41.</note> and that if no better way of putting us in possession of it can be struck out, we must apply to Parliament to alter our Act to meet the specific case. I dare say you will shortly hear from your legal adviser if you have not already done so.</p>
<p>Allan Fraser Esquire</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>I am always my Dear Sir| Most faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>