<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MISS MARION ELY,<note>Marion Elizabeth Ely (1820-1913), daughter of Charles Ely and Sara, <hi rend="italic">née</hi> Rutt; niece of Rachel Talfourd (1792-1875), wife of CD's friend Thomas Noon Talfourd (1795-1854).</note> 19 JANUARY 1859</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-17</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Lyon &amp; Turnbull online catalogue, Oct 2019.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="friends|social engagements">friends|social engagements</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>TAVISTOCK HOUSE

TAVISTOCK SQUARE, LONDON W.C.</placeName>
               <date when="">Wednesday Nineteenth January 1859</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Marion<note>In this, the first currently known letter to Marion since Feb 1855, CD shifts from “My Dear Miss Ely” to “My Dear Marion”. The tone of the letter suggests a long break in their correspondence.</note></salute>
         </opener>
         <p> I assure you with utmost truthfulness and heartiness, that the love of our old times is strong within me, and that I never see your handwriting – far less, yourself – without a genuine interest and affection. I would have gladly come tonight if it had been possible; but (as the girls<note>CD's daughters Mamie (1838-96) and Katey (1839-1929).</note> will tell you), I am doubly engaged, and have been so, a long long while.

</p>
<p>In the hope that we may make up a cheerful dinner here before long, and improvise a skirmishing dance after it, I send my love to Mary,<note>Mary Talfourd (1829-1901), daughter of Thomas and Rachel Talfourd; married since 1856 to William Wreford Major.</note> and am ever</p>
<p>Miss Ely.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>   Your faithful
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>