<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MESSRS L. HACHETTE ET CIE,<note>Publishers, of 14 rue Pierre-Sarrazin, founded in 1826 by Louis Christophe Hachette (1800-64); see further Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 7, p. 759n. CD had agreed terms with Hachette for the translation of all his published novels in Jan 1856 (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 8, pp. 22-3, 39-40).</note> 4 MAY 1860</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Pierre Bergé &amp;amp; associés catalogue, November 2010.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fr">French</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="A Tale of Two Cities|publishing|France|finances<">A Tale of Two Cities|publishing|France|finances</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      186</profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>TAVISTOCK HOUSE,|TAVISTOCK SQUARE, LONDON. W.C.</placeName>
               <date when="1860-05-04">Mardi 4 Mai, 1860.</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Messieurs

</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>J’ai reçu votre lettre avec beaucoup de plaisir. Je suis charmé que vous […]<note>“avez” written above word crossed out.</note> avez entrepris la traduction de “The Tale of Two Cities”,<note>The last episode appeared in <hi rend="italic">All the Year Round</hi>, II, 93-5, 26 Nov 59; the volume issue appeared 21 Nov. Translated as <hi rend="italic">Paris et Londres</hi> en 1793, 1861, by Mme Loreau in Hachette’s series, “Bibliothèque des meilleurs romans étrangers”.</note> et que cette ouvrage soit connue en France. Voila un de mes espoirs les plus ardents, en l’ecrivant. Suivant vos instructions, j’ai disposé sur vous (par le moyen de mes banquiers) à deux jours de vue, pour deux mille francs.<note>The original agreement (above) paid CD £440 for all his novels to that date; 2,000 francs was £80.</note> Veuillez accepter, Messieurs, mes remerciements et l’assurance de ma plus haute consideration.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>à Messrs. L. Hachette &amp;amp; Cie: CHARLES DICKENS
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>