<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> WILLIAM POWELL FRITH,<note>William Powell Frith (1819-1909; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), painter. Studied art at the Royal Academy schools. Exhibited at the British Institution 1839; at the Royal Academy 1840; ARA 1845; RA 1853. Painted several pictures of Dolly Varden in 1841 (after the publication of Barnaby Rudge), after which he became a friend of CD. John Forster commissioned the portrait <hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens in His Study</hi> from him in 1859.</note> 16 MAY 1864 </title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in International Autograph Auctions online catalogue, October 2016. On mourning paper.<note>Since the death of his mother on 12 Sept. 1863 CD generally wrote his letters on mourning paper.</note> </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="friends|clubs|visual arts|Barnaby Rudge">friends|clubs|visual arts|Barnaby Rudge</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>GAD'S HILL PLACE,

HIGHAM BY ROCHESTER, KENT.</placeName>
               <date when="1864-05-16">Monday Sixteenth May 1864</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Frith</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>The enclosed requisition<note>Prepared by CD for a meeting of the Garrick Club on 25 Apr 1864, to amend the rules for committee member retirement and re-election. In the end the resolution was not used; see To Lover, 21 May 1864, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 10, pp. 397-8.</note> (which speaks for itself as a plain matter) will require 20 signatures. Do you feel a sufficient interest in such a principle, to authorize me to add yours to it? You can tell me on Wednesday, and then give it me back. </p>
<p>W.P. Frith Esquire</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Ever Faithfully
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>