<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> JAMES BIRTLES,<note>James Birtles, printer, on staff of Charles Whiting, printer of <hi rend="italic">All the Year Round</hi>.</note> 6 NOVEMBER 1865</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-02-23</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS David J. Holmes Autographs. Address: Mr. James Birtles | Mr. Whiting’s.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="All the Year Round,editing,Doctor Marigold's Prescriptions">All the Year Round,editing,Doctor Marigold's Prescriptions</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>OFFICE OF ALL THE YEAR ROUND,</placeName>
               <date when="1865-11-06">Monday Sixth November 1865</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dr. Mr. Birtles</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I will send you round the <note>No doubt for<hi rend="italic"> All the Year Round</hi>, but not identified.</note> concluding folios of the enclosed paper2 at about noon to day. Tomorrow morning I will begin to make up the Xmas No.<note><hi rend="italic">Doctor Marigold’s Prescriptions</hi>, <hi rend="italic">All the Year Round</hi>  Xmas No., published 7 Dec 65. Birtles had by now received the first three stories (<hi rend="italic">To</hi> Birtles, 7 Nov, Pilgrim Letters 11). CD “made up” the No. with another five stories, including his own “To Be Taken with a Grain of Salt” and “To be Taken for Life”; he then spent 8 Nov with Births, “making up” the No. for printing, “always a tough job” (<hi rend="italic">To</hi> Lehmann, 7 Nov, Pilgrim Letters 11). Speed was essential: galley proofs had to be read and corrected, the rest of the MS typeset and finally the type broken up into double-column pages. The No. was in print by 17 Nov, when CD sent Charles Kent a confidential copy.</note> and will enable you to go on breaking it into pages. </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Faithfully yrs
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CD</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>