<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MARGUERITE POWER,<note>Marguerite Agnes Power (?1815-67; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), novelist; contributor of prose and poetry to <hi rend="italic">Household Words and All the Year Round</hi>. CD met her through her aunt, the Countess of Blessington (1789-1849). In 1857 CD, Thackeray, and John Forster raised a subscription of £200 for her; see To Thackeray, 4 Dec 1857, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 8, p. 486.</note> 19 JUNE 1866 </title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-09</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in University Archives online catalogue, November 2017. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id=""></interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
	<address>
	<addrLine>Miss Power | 26 Edmund Terrace | Notting Hill | London W. 
	</addrLine>
	</address>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>GAD’S HILL PLACE

HIGHAM BY ROCHESTER, KENT.</placeName>
               <date when="1866-06-19">Tuesday Nineteenth June 1866 </date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Marguerite</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I am extremely pleased with the Vine,<note>Thus in MS. Power was the author of the poem 'The Vines', <hi rend="italic">All the Year Round</hi> 15 (7 July 1866): 609-10.</note> as a charming and elegant little poem – in which I assuredly see no trace of the difficulty you speak of.<note>Possibly Power’s failing health; she suffered a spinal injury after a fall from a horse, and died after a long battle with cancer. See To Mrs Henderson, 4 July 1867, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 11, p. 390.</note> To the best of my belief it comes in innumerable cases – and (happily) goes. </p>
<p>Rest satisfied that I will gently explain exactly what you write on the other point, in the two quarters to which I have natural and easy access.<note> Untraced </note> I should have sent you this note sooner, but for having been away on a rest-trip after hard work. </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Affectionately Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CD</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>