<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> SAMUEL LACK MASON,<note>Samuel Lack Mason (1837-1889), General Manager of the North British Railway, operators of the east coast route in Scotland.</note> 14 DECEMBER 1868</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-03-22</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from facsimile in Jarndyce Dickens catalogue CLXV, 2005.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="travel|public readings|railway">travel|public readings|railway</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>Kennedy’s Hotel, Prince’s Street</placeName>
               <date when="1868-12-14">Monday Night Fourteenth December | 1868</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I beg to assure you that I am truly sensible of the kindness and courtesy of your letter received to-night, and that I thank you for it cordially. It will be a great comfort to me to avail myself of your most obliging offer<note>Mason, after attending a reading (presumably that of 11 Dec), arranged for a saloon carriage to be brought from King’s Cross for CD’s return to London, as more “convenient for sleeping in” than those available in Edinburgh: see <hi rend="italic">To</hi> Hogarth, 18 Dec 68, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 12, p. 251.</note> next Saturday night, by the 10 p.m. Train from here to King’s Cross.</p>
<p>Samuel L. Mason Esquire</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>