<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> CHARLES KENT,<note>William Charles Mark Kent (always known as Charles) (1823-1902; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), poet and journalist, editor and proprietor of the Sun.</note> 22 MAY 1868 </title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2021-01-31</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Replaces Extract in Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 12, p. 117. | Text from facsimile in Swann Auction Galleries online catalogue, May 2016.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id=""></interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>OFFICE OF ALLTHE YEAR ROUND</placeName>
               <date when="1868-05-22">Friday Twenty Second May 1868 </date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Kent.</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I cannot tell you how truly I feel your kind remembrance of your friend undersigned, or what delightful associations I shall always connect with the beautiful cigar case before me at this present writing. – Thank you! – </p>
<p>Since I came back<note>For W.H. Wills’s incapacitation after a fall from a horse see To Alfred Dickens, 16 May 1868, Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 12, p. 111.</note>, I have been so overwhelmed by six months of arrears of business, intensely complicated by the illness of Wills,3 that I have been constantly afflicted with a revolving nightmare. I hope however to send round “The Duke’s Motto”<note>Originally The Duke's Daughter; or <hi rend="italic">The Hunchback of Paris</hi>, adapted by John Brougham, first performed in England at the Lyceum, 1 Oct 63, with Charles Fechter as the hero; performed as The Duke's Motto in the Grecian Saloon, 18 Jan 64. Perhaps sent for review, but no notice of it appeared in Kent's Sun.</note>, this next week. I have been here – there – everywhere – and (most of all) nowhere – from the time of my re-beholding Euston Square.5 </p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Ever my Dear Kent |Your truly affectionate Friend
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>