<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> VICE ADMIRAL SIR SIDNEY DACRES,<note>Sir Sidney Colpoys Dacres (1805-84; <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>), Vice-Admiral 1865;Admiral 1870; KCB 1865; First Sea Lord 1868-72; see Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 11, p. 352n.</note> 1 AUGUST 1868</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-04-11</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>MS Huntington Library.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="family">family</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>1

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>GAD’S HILL PLACE, | HIGHAM BY ROCHESTER, KENT</placeName>
               <date when="1868-08-01">Saturday First August, 1868</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Sir Sydney<note>Possibly confused by writing to Sir Sidney about Sydney Smith Dickens (below), CD wrote Dacres’s name here “Sydney”; in the address line below he originally wrote “Sidney”, then overwrote “i” with “y”.</note> Dacres</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I hear from Captain Buckley of the <hi rend="italic">Pylades</hi><note>Sydney Smith Dickens (below) served on the Pylades 1867-68; he joined the Zealous 1868.</note> that he has recommended my son<note>Sydney Smith Dickens (1847-72), CD’s seventh child and fifth son. Entered the Royal Navy, Sep 1860, and trained on board the <hi rend="italic">Britannia</hi> at Portsmouth (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 9, pp. 309, 316 &amp; nn). Midshipman, Dec 1861 (Pilgrim Letters 9, pp. 542 &amp; n, 543) and appointed to the Orlando, Dec 1861. Served on the <hi rend="italic">Pelican</hi>, June 1864-67, joining the Pylades, July 1867, where he advanced to Acting Sub-Lt (Aug 1867) and Sub- Lt (Nov 1867).</note> for promotion to a Death-vacancy<note>Though Buckley presumably wanted to promote him, Sydney joined the Zealous as Sub-Lt, Aug 1868.</note> on board his ship. He is kind enough to tell me that he has done so, because my son knows his profession well, and is a zealous and bright officer. If you can serve him again,<note>As Dacre had done in some way (Apr 1867), when Sydney was sent home on sick leave, having contracted African Coast fever (Pilgrim <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> 11, pp. 352, 367).</note> I hope he will always do credit to your favorable remembrance.</p>
<p>Vice Admiral | Sir Sydney Dacres | K.C.B.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Alwys Yours | Faithfully and obliged
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>