<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><hi rend="italic">To</hi> MRS LYNN LINTON, 21 JUNE 1869</title>
            <author>
               <orgName>The Charles Dickens Letters Project</orgName>
            </author>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Charles Dickens Letters Project</hi>, ed. Leon Litvack, Katie Brandt, Emily Bell, and Jeremy Parrott (London: Dickens Fellowship), DickensLetters.com.</bibl>
            <respStmt xml:id="EB">
               <resp>Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>Aisling Reid</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName>The Dickens Fellowship</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <date>2022-02-13</date>
            <availability>
               <p>No part of any work within this web-based publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means, electronic mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the Editor of <hi rend="italic">The Dickensian</hi>, acting in behalf of the publishers, the Dickens Fellowship.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text from Swann Auction Galleries catalogue, Oct 2002.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <interpGrp type="themes">
            <interp xml:id="friends,editing,All the Year Round">friends,editing,All the Year Round</interp>
         </interpGrp>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
      <body>
         <opener>
            <dateline>
               <placeName>OFFICE OF ALL THE YEAR ROUND,</placeName>
               <date when="1869-06-21">Monday Twenty First June 1869</date>
            </dateline>
            <salute>My Dear Mrs. Linton</salute>
         </opener>
         <p>I had not the least intention of returning you the enclosed paper,<note>Clearly Mrs Linton had asked CD to return her review of John Forster’s <hi rend="italic">Biography</hi> of Walter Savage Landor. <hi rend="italic">Fraser’s Magazine</hi>, N. S. Vol. II, July 70 published an article by her entitled “Reminiscences of Walter Savage Landor” in which she endeavoured “to redress, by my testimony, the unjust balance of public opinion by which he has been weighed only according to his demerits”; although she mentions both Forster and Dickens, nowhere does she refer to Forster’s book; no review with the opening words quoted by Layard (<hi rend="italic">To Eliza Lynn Linton</hi>, 19 June 1869, <hi rend="italic">n</hi>) yet discovered.</note> and had ordered it – in right of our long association – to be placed to your credit in the business account. That order I shall certainly not cancel (except under compulsion) but you are perfectly free to publish the paper nevertheless.</p>
         <closer>
            <salute>Believe me Very faithfully Yours
            </salute>
            <signed>
               <persName>CHARLES DICKENS</persName>
            </signed>
         </closer>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>